<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlsn="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Lettera scritta dal Principe Alberto alla Regina Victoria durante il loro fidanzamento (15 novembre 1839)</title>
				<author>Principe Alberto di Sassonia-Coburgo-Gotha</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Encoded by:</resp>
					<name xml:id="FS"> Federica Saviotti </name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Royal Archives</publisher>
				<availability>
					Questo testo è stato pubblicato con il consenso di sua maestà la Regina Elisabetta II, il contenuto appartiene alla Royal Collection Trust. Non è consentito l'utilizzo delle immagini per uso pubblicitario senza il consenso della Royal Collection Trust.
				</availability>
				<date>2016</date>
			<idno type="rct.uk">https://www.rct.uk/collection/themes/exhibitions/treasures-from-the-royal-archives/windsor-castle/ra-vicmainz29624</idno>
			<idno type="ra">RA VIC/MAIN/Z/296/24</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblFull>
				<titleStmt>Letter from Prince Albert to Queen Victoria written during their engagement, 15 november 1839, Windsor Castle, Royal Collection Trust</titleStmt>
					<address>
					<addrLine>The Royal Archives</addrLine>
					<addrLine>Round Tower</addrLine>
					<addrLine>Windsor Castle</addrLine>
					<addrLine>Windsor</addrLine>
					<addrLine>Berkshire SL4 1NJ</addrLine>
					</address>
				</biblFull>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
				<encodingDesc>
					<editorialDecl>
					<p>Testo preservato nella sua interezza durante la trascrizione.</p>
				</editorialDecl>
				</encodingDesc>
			
			<listPerson type="real">
  <person xml:id="Principe Alberto">
   <persName>Alberto di Sassonia-Coburgo-Gotha</persName>
   <abbr>Albert</abbr>
   <note>Principe Alberto, consorte della regina Victoria del Regno unito.</note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="Regina Victoria">
   <persName>Regina Victoria del Regno Unito</persName>
   <abbr>Victoria</abbr>
   <note>Regina Victoria del Regno unito, promessa sposa di Alberto.</note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="Ernesto I">
   <persName>Ernesto I di Sassonia-Coburgo-Gotha</persName>
   <abbr>Ernest</abbr>
   <note>Duca di Sassonia-Coburgo-Gotha, padre del Principe Alberto.</note>
  </person>
  <person xml:id="Louise Lehzen">
   <persName>Johanna Clara Louise Lehzen, Baroness of Lehzen</persName>
   <abbr>B Lehzen</abbr>
   <note>Fu la governante della giovane Regina Victoria.</note>
  </person>
</listPerson>
<profileDesc>
	<creation>
		<date>1839</date>
	</creation>
	<langUsage>
		<language ident="en">English</language>
	</langUsage>
	<textDesc n="letter">
	</textDesc>
</profileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
	<front>
		<body>
	<head>Dearest deeply loved Victoria.</head>

<p>According to your wish, and by the urging of my heart to talk to you and open my heart to you, I send these lines. We arrived safely at Calais, and Lord Alfred [Paget] is to re-cross in a ¼ of an hour, and will arrive at Windsor early tomorrow. The state of the tide and strong wind forced us to start at 2.30 in the morning, and we reached here at about 6 o’clock. Even then the Firebrand could not approach the quay, so that we decided to go ashore in a smaller boat. We both, Schenk, and all the servants were fearfully ill; I have hardly recovered yet.</p>
<p>I need not tell you that since we left, all my thoughts have been with you at Windsor, and that your image fills my whole soul. Even in my dreams I never imagined that I should find so much love on earth. How that moment shines for me still when I was close to you, with your hand in mine. Those days flew by so quickly, but our separation will fly equally so.</p>

<p>Ernest wishes me to say a thousand nice things to you.</p>

<p>With promises of unchanging love and devotion
Your ever true
Albert.
My best respects to dear Aunt and B[aroness] Lehzen</p>
</body>
</front>
</text>
</TEI>

			